<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A victory obtained by Lieut: Gen: David Lesley, in the north of Scotland, against Colonell Hurrey and his forces; and the number killed and taken. Also, the declaration and resolution of the inhabitants of York-shire, Cumberland, Sunderland, and the bishoprick of Durham, for the Parliament of England; and the desires of the English army in the north, touching Scotland. Together, with the further proceedings of the Treaty at Breda, the sending of a message to the Emperour of Germany and the Duke of Saxony, by Captain Swan, with an answer thereunto, in relation to the affairs of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E600_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206394</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865554</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865554</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E600[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A victory obtained by Lieut: Gen: David Lesley, in the north of Scotland, against Colonell Hurrey and his forces; and the number killed and taken. Also, the declaration and resolution of the inhabitants of York-shire, Cumberland, Sunderland, and the bishoprick of Durham, for the Parliament of England; and the desires of the English army in the north, touching Scotland. Together, with the further proceedings of the Treaty at Breda, the sending of a message to the Emperour of Germany and the Duke of Saxony, by Captain Swan, with an answer thereunto, in relation to the affairs of England.</title>
                  <author>Michel, Peter, fl. 1648-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Wood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Peter Michel.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 9.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newark, David Leslie, --  Baron, d. 1682 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Urry, John, --  Sir, d. 1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165619:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VICTORY <hi>OBTAINED</hi> By Lieut: Gen: David Leſley, In the
North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt Colonell <hi>Hurrey</hi> and his forces;
and the number killed and taken.</p>
            <p>ALSO, The Declaration and Reſolution of the Inhabitants of
<hi>York-ſhire, Cumberland, Sunderland,</hi> and the Biſhoprick of
<hi>Durham,</hi> for the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> And the deſires of
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in the North, touching <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With the further proceedings of the Treaty at
<hi>Breda,</hi> the ſending of a Meſſage to the Emperour of
<hi>Germany</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> by Captain <hi>Swan,</hi>
with an Anſwer thereunto, in relation to the affairs of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Wood.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:165619:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165619:2"/>
            <head>A Victory obtained by Lieutenant Generall <hi>David
Leſley,</hi> in the North of <hi>Scotland;</hi> against Colonell
<hi>Hurrey</hi> and his forces, and the number killed and taken.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am ſo much your Servant, that I muſt wait upon you, and
attend the motion of your perſonall reſidence; and though my Letters are
long ere they arrive, yet I hope at laſt they will have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to
kiſſe your hand; and I beſeech you permit them ſo to do, and with as
much affection as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, from a perſon whom you have ſuffered to
be acquainted with your worth, and have ſo infinitely obliged; which makes me
very unhappy, that I can neither ſay or do any thing accordingly. However,
give me leave to entertain you with what is done on the other ſide of
<hi>Tweed;</hi> which I here humbly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by communicating theſe
enſuing lines to your tender object, and favourable conſtruction.</p>
            <p>This morning, here arrived a Meſſenger from
<hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with ſeverall Letters to Gentlemen of quality in theſe
parts, intimating the tranſaction of affairs between the Committee of
Eſtates, Clergy, and Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; And amongſt the reſt, he makes mention of a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165619:3"/>great blow given to <hi>Renegado
Hurry</hi> (and his party) near <hi>Caithneſs,</hi> in the North of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thus:</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Hurrey</hi> (that grand <hi>Renegado-Artist</hi>)
have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing landed a conſiderable party, conſiſting of about 2000 horſe
and foot, preſently endeavoured to leave no means unattempted, that might
prove inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal for the carrying on of the royal intereſt and deſign,
and likewiſe for the fomenting of new Commotions. The Committee of Eſtates
timely fore-ſeeing the ſad event that might happen and enſue thereupon,
forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with reſolved to expedite a potent power againſt them; and
accordingly gave inſtructions to Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall <hi>David
Leſley,</hi> to iſſue forth Orders for a generall Rendezvous of the
horſe and foot in thoſe parts; to the end, he might ſpeedily take the
field, and be in a poſture of oppoſition, to retard the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies farther
march Southward: This being with ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity facilitated, the ſaid Lieutenant
Generall took his march towards the North, and (as it is ſaid) on the 28 of
<hi>April</hi> laſt, marched towards <hi>Caithneſs;</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy having
intelligence of their advance, muſtred up all his forces, and Colonell
<hi>Hurrey</hi> (Commander in chief of that Brigade) having all his men in
readineſſe, fell ſuddainly upon Generall <hi>Leſley</hi>'s men, and
aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them couragiouſly, but they being provided for them, gallantly
reſiſted them, and forced them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat: The firſt of this inſtant,
the Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall having united all his forces together, gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
to Colonell <hi>Humes</hi> to advance with a party of Horſe towards the
Enemy, who according to Order, charged Colonell <hi>Hurrey</hi>'s horſe, and
exchanged ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vollies, and were received with great gallantry,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165619:3"/>being moſt of them old Soldates, and
well knew how to withſtand the fury of an enemy; but being at the laſt
over-powred, they retreated to the next Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and Colonell <hi>Humes</hi>
his men returned to their main Body. Within a while after, their Bodies
joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the conflict grew very hot, which put them all in a great heat,
notwithſtanding their being in a cold Climate. The victory ſeemed
ſomewhat dubious for a while, for Colonell <hi>Hurrey</hi> and his men fought
very gallantly, and for the ſpace of two hours very manfully maintained their
groud, but (having not many horſe, and they being over-powred by Generall
<hi>Leſley</hi>'s) were forced to deſert their foot; then Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<hi>Leſley</hi>'s men (upon routing of the horſe) ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly fell in
among the foot, and by main force and violence broke their ranks, diſordering
their Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, and putting all to the ſword that ſtood in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
and defiance, which befell the <hi>Zwitzers</hi> in no ſmall number, for many
of their fiery ſpirits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied quarter; but thoſe that deſired that
martiall priviledge, had the ſame granted. In this great blow, (we hear) that
the Lord <hi>Napier</hi> is wounded, and that <hi>Renegado Hurrey</hi> is taken
priſoner, being very dangerouſly wounded; who is now like to ſing a
moſt dolefull tune, to his ſeverall <hi>Changes.</hi> It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry credibly
reported, that there were killed, rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and taken priſoners, two
thouſand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the <hi>Hurronians,</hi> and that the aforeſaid
Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generall <hi>David Leſley,</hi> returned triumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with
ſeverall trophees of his victory (having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all their armes and
ammunition, and divers pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners) with the loſſe of about 300 men, and
ſome 350 wounded.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165619:4"/>
            <p>The reſt of the Confederate-royaliſts in the North, (it's
ſaid) are making what haſte poſſible they can towards the Mountains,
and many diſcontented ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (who ſeemed not a little active for the
propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating and carrying on of the deſigne) begins now to ſing a ſong of
<hi>Recantation;</hi> ſo that (it is believed) the <hi>flames</hi> are
already quenched which began ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to break forth: notwithſtanding,
the great talk of the Treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> for an Agreement, and new forces
to be ſpeedily landed; for that goes on but ſlowly, and [perhaps] <hi>may
be ended, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Army comes to</hi> Edenborough. The
<hi>Scots</hi> know their [declared] King is young, neceſſitous, and with a
<hi>divided-Councell,</hi> and are ſtedfaſtly reſolved to deal with him
accordingly; for unleſſe he will come to their terms, <hi>he must expect
nothing from them.</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (if I may tell you my thoughts) I conceive he is
in a ſad condition; for the <hi>States</hi> are weary of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there,
and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſits but looſe in the ſaddle himſelf,
therefore the <hi>Scots</hi> are not to be diſcommended, in ſeeking to make
good conditions.</p>
            <p>Having given you a word or two of the Treaty, I ſhall preſent
you with the lateſt Intelligence which we have received from
<hi>Germany.</hi> The declared King of <hi>Scotland</hi> having ſent Captain
<hi>Swan</hi> to the Emperor, as an Embaſſadour (and after to the Duke of
<hi>Saxony</hi>) received this anſwer from the Emperour. That he condoled
with him for his fathers death <hi>[and that with a great invective against the
Parliament]</hi> withall telling him, the poor and unable condition that
<hi>Germany</hi> was in; yet he promiſed to do his beſt, when the allyed
Crowns, and Neighbours, and the united Provinces ſhould be a preſident, for
he muſt regulate himſelf by <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165619:4"/>them. But
it is believed, all their negotiations and ſubtle actings will be
fruſtrated, and ſuddenly blaſted in the bud; for in <hi>Scotland</hi>
they ſtill play <hi>fast and looſe,</hi> and good reaſon they have, for
miſery is haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon them, if they preſume to attempt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
invaſion, which to prevent, the ſouldiery in theſe parts ſeem both
unanimous and reſolved; being alſo ſeconded with an invitation from the
well affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>York-ſhire, Sunderland, Cumberland,</hi> and
<hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who are reſolved to ſtand cloſe to them, for the
preſervation of their Countries, lives, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, againſt the force
and violence of any invaders whatſoever; And declaring, That they will be
obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the <hi>preſent Government,</hi> and give their utmoſt aid and
aſſiſtance againſt all perſons whatſoever, that ſhall endeavour
to aboliſh and extirpate the ſame: Yet notwithſtanding, many there are in
theſe parts, who walk too much averſe to their ſteps, deſiring a
change, &amp;c. As the daughters of <hi>Pelias</hi> King of
<hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> did, who hearkning to the counſell and advice of
<hi>Medea,</hi> ſuffered their old decrepit father to be boiled in a Chaldron
with herbs, perſwading the people, <hi>that nothing was more available, for
the reſtauration of him to his former youth.</hi> Even ſo, when
<hi>ſelf-ended</hi> ſpirits, carry eloquence in the one hand, and
ſubtilty in the other (under the pretence of <hi>Reformation in
Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) they immediately cut the Commonwealth in pieces; as theſe
turbulent ſpirits in theſe parts would do, who (by their fair eloquent
deluſions, for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi>) endeavour to alienate and withdraw the
hearts of the people, from their due obedience to the <hi>preſent
Authority,</hi> and ſeeketh nothing more then the ruinating of the
<hi>Preſervers of Englands Liberties,</hi> and <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165619:5"/>caſting
all the fruit of their labours and indefatigable pains, into a Chaos and
labyrinth of miſery. <hi>Sir,</hi> fearing that I have been too tedious, be
pleaſed to excuſe him, who remains</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your obliged friend, to ſerve you:</hi> PETER
MICHEL.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kendall,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 4. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I remain ſtill in the Regiment of renowned Major
Generall <hi>Lambert,</hi> our horſe and foot have had a Rendezvous, and we
expect [and hope] to croſſe the River <hi>Tweed</hi> very ſuddainly; the
ſouldiery deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing more then to fight <hi>Jockey</hi> once again,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he complains, that he cannot be ſatisfied, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carliſle</hi> be ſurrendred to him; in lieu
whereof, we are deſirous to give him a full and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall payment, for the
<hi>interest</hi> of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, P. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
